Started. Alright בוקר טוב. boker tov. So today's דף daf is ס"ח.
samech-ches. We start the new פרק. perek. We'll start again from the
very bottom of ס"ז עמוד ב', samech-zayin amud bais, the new משנה.
mishna. We read it yesterday but let's start it again. Okay כלל
גדול אמרו בשבת. klal gadol amru b'shabbos. So they said a large
principle regarding שבת. Shabbos. And again as I mentioned the other day,
we have done six פרקים prakim about preparing for ערב שבת erev
Shabbos and now we are finally getting into שבת Shabbos proper. Okay
so they said a large principle regarding שבת: Shabbos: כל השוכח עיקר
שבת ועשה מלאכות הרבה בשבתות הרבה. kol hashocheiach ikar Shabbos v'asa melachos
harbei b'shabbatos harbei. If somebody forgets the whole principle of שבת, Shabbos,
they forget there's such a thing as שבת Shabbos in the תורה.
Torah. And they wind up doing many different מלאכות melachos on many
different שבתות, Shabbatos, אינו חייב אלא חטאת אחת, eino chayav ela chatas
achas, and then sometime they are told and remember oh my god
there was such a thing as שבת Shabbos for the last ten
years I've not been doing it. So they only bring one חטאת
chatas because it was really only one mistake, they forgot that such
a thing as שבת Shabbos existed, everything else derives from that.
היודע עיקר שבת ועשה מלאכות הרבה בשבתות הרבה. hayodea ikar Shabbos v'asa
melachos harbei b'shabbatos harbei. Somebody knows that there is such a principle
as שבת Shabbos and they do many different מלאכות melachos on many
different שבתות, Shabbatos, right? So you know there's שבת, Shabbos, so what
was your mistake? So it's not set explicitly but as the גמרא
Gemara understands, your mistake is you forgot which day was שבת. Shabbos.
Let's say you got your days mixed up or each week you
got your days mixed up, maybe it was one mistake, maybe it
was multiple mistakes, but what you forgot was on a particular each
particular שבת Shabbos you forgot that that day was שבת. Shabbos. So
in that case, חייב על כל שבת ושבת. chayav al kol Shabbos
v'shabbos. You're חייב chayav for every שבת Shabbos because that was your
mistake, each שבת Shabbos that you forgot that today was שבת. Shabbos.
So it's a different mistake each שבת Shabbos that each week you
forgot that it was שבת. Shabbos. So even if you did, you
know, twenty מלאכות melachos each שבת, Shabbos, it's only one mistake essentially
each week and therefore it's one חטאת. chatas. What's the first case
then? That you forgot such a thing as שבת Shabbos existed. Okay
here you know such a thing as שבת Shabbos exists but every
week you forget which day is שבת. Shabbos. Now the question was
asked let's say it was really only one forgetting, you know you
forgot one week and then and you got your days mixed up
and then everything else was an outgrowth of that. Nevertheless the גמרא
Gemara says that objectively those are defined as different acts of like
different things because each week it's a different sort of mistake although
it all derives from the first mistake. But we'll see that in
the גמרא. Gemara. But in that case you only bring for each
שבת. Shabbos. Now היודע שהוא שבת ועשה מלאכות הרבה בשבתות הרבה. hayodea
shehu Shabbos v'asa melachos harbei b'shabbatos harbei. You know it's שבת Shabbos
and you wind up doing מלאכות melachos because you forget that this
מלאכה melacha or you didn't know that this מלאכה melacha is forbidden.
So חייב על כל אב מלאכה ומלאכה. chayav al kol av melacha
u'melacha. You're חייב chayav not for for every separate אב מלאכה. av
melacha. So let's say for
example every week? No, at least it doesn't sound that way in
the משנה. mishna. Some of this is discussed in another גמרא Gemara
but it's not the way the משנה mishna sounds like. So let's
say you didn't know you never knew or you forgot that you're
not allowed to water your plants on שבת. Shabbos. So over ten
שבתות Shabboses you watered your plants. So you only bring one חטאת
chatas because it was one thing you got wrong about you didn't
know you're not allowed to water your plants on שבת. Shabbos. Let's
say you didn't know you're not allowed to water your plants and
you didn't know you're not allowed to I don't know light a
fire and you did that every שבת Shabbos over ten שבתות. Shabboses.
You'd bring two חטאת chatas one for forgetting about watering the plants
and and one for about lighting a fire. Now Michael says you
could sort of say in that case you should bring the number
of מלאכות melachos times the number of שבתות Shabbatos because maybe each
שבת Shabbos also makes it separate. But that's debated in another גמרא
Gemara not actually interestingly in our גמרא Gemara and it does not
sound that way from this משנה. mishna. From this משנה mishna sounds
like if the fundamental mistake is about the מלאכה melacha then you
bring according to the מלאכות. melachos. Now ועושה מלאכות הרבה מעין מלאכה
אחת. v'oseh melachos harbei m'ein melacha achas.
Let's say you do many different מלאכות melachos all of the same
essence of the same מלאכה melacha which if you take my example
of watering, watering is a תולדה toldah a derivation of the מלאכה
melacha of the main category of planting. Anything that is done to
cause growth of of plants. So therefore let's say you on one
שבת Shabbos watered and planted and pruned and fertilized, it could be
ten different plants whatever. Anyway but those are all in the same
category as planting. So in that case אינו חייב אלא חטאת אחת.
eino chayav ela chatas achas. You would only bring one sin offering
because they all fall in the same category. Okay so there's a
lot of חידושים chidushim here. Number one is the idea that we
take the various מלאכות melachos and we organize them by categories. We're
going to see in the next משנה mishna that says that there
are thirty-nine מלאכות, melachos, thirty-nine אבות avos main categories and the גמרא
Gemara then and we'll say this tomorrow but I'll say it right
now says what's the point of listing them as thirty-nine categories? Meaning
okay maybe it's a helpful organizational principle but you know what difference
would it make if we would conflate some categories or we would
expand them more? What's the significance halachic significance of thirty-nine? And it
says to tell you that you could bring up to thirty-nine sin
offerings for one שבת. Shabbos. That if you forget every single מלאכה
melacha so then the question is how do you remember it's שבת
Shabbos but we'll worry about that later. If you forget every single
מלאכה... melacha... and you would bring thirty-nine different sin offerings. Each different
אב מלאכה av melacha is considered a different sin. Now that's a
חידוש, chiddush, because you could have thought to say, look,
if I eat different parts of a נבלה, neveilah, right, I eat
from the hindquarters and I eat from the ribs and I eat
whatever, it's still all one sin of eating a נבלה. neveilah. So
if I violate שבת Shabbos in multiple different ways, by planting and
turning on a light and cooking and all these types of things,
it's just different ways of violating שבת. Shabbos. So maybe it should
be doing the same sin over and over and over again. I
just violated שבת Shabbos in slightly different ways. So the חידוש chiddush
is that no, the different מלאכות melachos are considered as different sins
and therefore different sin offerings. So the first חידוש chiddush is that
there are thirty-nine categories and if you forget that it's שבת, Shabbat,
again, this is unintentional, not intentional, you forget let's say not שבת,
Shabbat, you forget these things are forbidden, you will bring a different
sin offering for each category. But within the category, everything that goes
under the big heading cooking, cooking, baking, frying, all those things, everything
that goes under the big heading of planting, planting, watering, fertilizing, all
of those, they're all one category and if you do them even
all those different things since they're in the same category, you bring
one sin offering. All of this is unintentional when you forgot that
these were forbidden. So that's חידוש chiddush number one, that we divide
by categories on the one hand, you could bring up to thirty-nine
sin offerings for one שבת, Shabbat, but on the other hand, multiple
different things in one category is only one sin offering. The next
חידוש chiddush of the משנה, mishna, of the beginning of the משנה,
mishna, I jumped to the end, the beginning of the משנה mishna
is basically telling you depending on where your mistake is. Did you
forget שבת Shabbos existed altogether? You forgot today was שבת. Shabbos. You
forgot this מלאכה melacha was forbidden. That will determine also the number
of sin offerings based on where your error was. If your error
was on שבת, Shabbat, then your sin offerings is based on the
number of שבתות. Shabbatot. If your error is this act is forbidden,
then it's based on the number of different categories that you forgot
and that you went ahead and violated. Yes, Michael?
My first name is correct, then the first case is that you
did not know the שבת. Shabbat. In which case then I'm very
surprised at the imprecision of the language because you can't forget something
you never knew, right? כל השכח עיקר שבת, kol hashocheach ikar Shabbat,
if we say כל השכח kol hashocheach we mean you...
No, you knew. No, no, we'll discuss that in the גמרא. Gemara.
For now, we're assuming you were once told it was שבת Shabbat
and then somehow you forgot about it. Yes.
Most of the categories of מלאכה melacha are not explicitly mentioned in
the תורה. Torah. It's unusual to have to bring a חטאת chatat
for something that's not...
Well, it is bringing a חטאת chatat for the violation of שבת.
Shabbat. The חידוש chiddush here is that it is to bring multiple
ones, right? And that's all based on the fact that חז"ל Chazal
understand that even though it's not written in the תורה, Torah, this
becomes the binding meaning of what שבת Shabbat violation is. Okay, so
let's, you know what, trust me on this Michael, we'll get to
it. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא תנא
כלל גדול? Mai taama tana klal gadol? So the גמרא Gemara starts
with a much more technical question which is like a very sort
of almost linguistic question before getting to the meat of it. Why
does it say כלל גדול, klal gadol, a big כלל? klal? Like
you know, says you know,
like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, זה כלל גדול בתורה ואהבת לרעך כמוך,
zeh klal gadol baTorah va’ahavta l’reiacha kamocha, right? Why a big one?
Why not just כלל? klal? So now and now we're going to
get into almost the whole עמוד amud or two-thirds of the עמוד
amud about this linguistic question. And I want to make a point
about this. The next,
the section we're about to read sounds like often the opening of
a מסכת. masechet. The opening of a מסכת masechet will often focus
on
some side marginal linguistic issue and spend some time analyzing it, maybe
bringing in other סוגיות sugyos and other parallels but about the sort
of more secondary type of a question, like everybody knows the beginning
of קידושין Kiddushin is like that and so on. And I just
hypothesize that because that this might have been seen as like the
כלל גדול klal gadol as like a almost like a new beginning
of a מסכת, masechet, not literally a beginning of a מסכת, masechet,
but almost like you know, now we're getting into a different section
of שבת. Shabbat. So we have almost frankly something that sounds like
an opening סוגיא sugya that you would normally expect at the beginning
of a מסכת. masechet. So let's take a look. מאי טעמא תנא
כלל גדול? Mai taama tana klal gadol? Why did we pick a
big principle? אילימא משום דקבעי למתני עוד כלל אחר, Ilima mishum dekaba’ei
l’misni od klal achair, if it's because he wanted to teach another
כלל אחר, klal achair, תנא כלל גדול, tana klal gadol, so we
said כלל גדול klal gadol because later we're going to say that
there's another כלל klal they said by שבת Shabbat which is about
a much smaller point about how what is the not in this
משנה mishna but a later משנה mishna about what is the minimum
size that you have to carry. So it's כלל אמרו בשבת klal
amru beShabbat about the minimum size of things for carrying. So you
know what, that's not so big, that's not as all encompassing.
So therefore, that's why we said כלל גדול. klal gadol. So וגבי
שביעית נמי, V’gabei Shevi’is nami, now by שביעית, Shevi'is, שביעית Shevi'is also
opens with כלל גדול אמרו בשביעית, klal gadol amru beShevi’is, okay, a
big principle they said by שביעית Shevi’is and there it also
was about what types of foods are obligated in שביעית. Shevi’is. Anybody
want to guess which פרק perek begins כלל גדול אמרו
בשביעית?
klal gadol
amru beShevi’is? שביעי. Shevi’i. There you go. I really don't think that
was circumstantial. Seventh פרק perek of שבת, Shabbat, seventh פרק perek of
שביעית, Shevi’is, right? Seven years, seven days of the week. Okay, כלל
גדול אמרו בשבת, klal gadol amru beShabbat, כלל גדול אמרו בשביעית. klal
gadol amru beShevi’is. So the כלל גדול בשביעית klal gadol beShevi’is starts
about what types of foods are obligated in שביעית. Shevi’is. So then
why is that גדול? Gadol? So משום דקבעי למתני עוד כלל אחר
mishum dekabai l'misnei od klal acher because later as you get into
שביעית Shvi'it it will tell you another כלל klal which is not
maybe as big of a scope so it tells you כלל גדול.
klal gadol. If that's the reason, והא גבי מעשר דקתני במעשר veha
gabai ma'aser de-ktani be-ma'aser it says כלל כלל אחר klal klal acher
and it doesn't say כלל גדול? klal gadol? By מעשר ma'aser in
מסכת מעשר masechet ma'aser it starts כלל אמרו במעשר klal amru ba-ma'aser
and then later it says כלל אמרו klal amru and it doesn't
say כלל גדול klal gadol by the first one. So how come
here for the first כלל klal it's כלל גדול klal gadol by
שביעית shvi'it and שבת shabbat and not by מעשר? ma'aser? Now תוספות
tosafot makes an interesting point or he says I don't get it
by מעשר ma'aser the two כללים klalim are roughly the same scope
so what's the חידוש? chiddush? It's not just because it's first, it's
because it's first and it's bigger than the one that's going to
follow it. But whatever it is, that's the גמרא's gemara's question. Why
doesn't it say כלל גדול klal gadol by מעשר? ma'aser? So the
גמרא gemara says אלא, ela, where
am I? So אמר רבי יוסי בר אבין, amar Rabbi Yossi bar
Avin, שבת ושביעית דאית בהו אבות ואית בהו תולדות. Shabbat ve-Shvi'it de-is
behu avot ve-is behu toldot. שבת Shabbat and שביעית Shvi'it have אבות
מלאכה, avot melacha, have like thirty-nine major categories and have descendants, have
sub-categories, have things that are you know that are derived from those
categories. Like I said, you planting is the main, you know, putting
manure, watering, pruning, those are all תולדות. toldot. So therefore it is
the idea of אבות ותולדות avot ve-toldot is a כלל גדול klal
gadol like you know it's this whole big major categories.
So therefore, now שביעית shvi'it also have אבות ותולדות. avot ve-toldot. Why
does שביעית shvi'it have אבות ותולדות? avot ve-toldot? Because by שביעית shvi'it
the תורה Torah only mentions four things you're not allowed to do.
שדך לא תזרע וכרמך לא תזמור, sadcha lo tizra ve-charmecha lo tizmor,
don't plant or prune your vine, plant, plant your seeds or prune
your vine. And then it says את ספיח קצירך לא תקצור, et
sefiach ketzircha lo tiktzor,
don't harvest your grain, ואת ענבי נזירך לא תבצור, ve-et invey nezirecha
lo tivtzor, and do not harvest your grapes. So those are the
only מלאכות melachot the תורה Torah explicitly says don't do on שביעית.
shvi'it. But we understand that those are major categories, אבות, avot, and
then there are תולדות, toldot, they're derived categories that you also cannot
do on שביעית. shvi'it. So maybe because שביעית shvi'it and שבת shabbat
are like big things they have אבות ותולדות avot ve-toldot it says
כלל גדול. klal gadol. Now כלל גדול klal gadol though it's interesting,
by here the כלל גדול klal gadol is about the idea of
the אבות avot and the תולדות, toldot, these major categories. By שביעית
shvi'it it's not the case. By שביעית shvi'it it says כלל גדול
אמרו בשביעית klal gadol amru ba-shvi'it and it speaks about what types
of plants or whatever שביעית shvi'it applies to, not about the אבות
ותולדות. avot ve-toldot. So גדול gadol here doesn't really mean like the
כלל klal is גדול, gadol, it means like a כלל klal is
said by this I don't know גדול gadol category. It's a little
strange the way putting these things together because you understand the point
here the כלל klal is about the אבות avot and the תולדות.
toldot. By שביעית shvi'it the כלל klal is about what foods, what
plants are obligated, not about the idea of אבות ותולדות. avot ve-toldot.
But nevertheless these are like big areas of הלכה halacha so some
כלל klal that applies to this big topic that has אבות avot
and תולדות toldot therefore we're saying it. Now of course what the
גמרא's gemara's also doing is it's encouraging us to draw the parallel
between שביעית shvi'it and שבת. shabbat. I mean they're both seven days,
seven here. As I said, the כלל גדול's klal gadol's in both
of them begin in the seventh פרק perek and therefore it's saying
there's another parallel of אבות ותולדות. avot ve-toldot. So that also seems
to be part of the message it's getting across although it doesn't
really explain why it uses the phrase כלל גדול. klal gadol. Nevertheless,
let's see what the גמרא gemara answers.
So it
says מעשר דלית בהו אבות ותולדות ma'aser de-leit behu avot ve-toldot לא
תני כלל גדול. lo tani klal gadol. So therefore by מעשר ma'aser
this concept doesn't apply it didn't say כלל גדול. klal gadol. But
one minute, ולבר קפרא דתני כלל גדול במעשר ve-le-Bar Kappara de-tani klal
gadol be-ma'aser in Bar Kappara's version of the משנה mishna he has
כלל גדול klal gadol written by מעשר. ma'aser. So מאי אבות ומאי
תולדות איכא? mai avot ve-mai toldot ika? So where that can't be
based on the concept of אבות avot and תולדות toldot because it
doesn't exist by מעשר. ma'aser. So גדול gadol cannot be a category
that has אבות avot and תולדות toldot because why? It would explain
why מעשר ma'aser doesn't have it but it wouldn't explain Bar Kappara's
version of the משנה mishna that has it by מעשר. ma'aser. אלא
לאו היינו טעמא גדול, ela lav hainu ta'ama gadol, עונשו של שבת
חמור משל שביעית. onsho shel Shabbat chamur mi-shel Shvi'it. Here's the reason
it's גדול. gadol. It's גדול gadol because again, not that the כלל
klal is said about the גדול gadol aspect but it's an important
category. שבת Shabbat is a very weighty category. Why is it a
weighty category? The punishment of שבת Shabbat is much is greater than
that of שביעית. shvi'it. First of all שבת shabbat you're like חייב
מיתה, chayav mita, שביעית shvi'it is just a לאו. lav. But the
גמרא gemara also says another way also the scope of it. דאילו
שבת איתא בין בתלוש בין במחובר. de-ilu Shabbat ita bein be-talush bein
be-mechubar. שבת Shabbat you can't do מלאכה melacha whether the thing is
attached to the ground or cut from the ground, right? You can't
knead dough, you know, it doesn't you know, you can't make a
fire, it has nothing to do with only things that are in
the on the ground. ואילו שביעית ve-ilu Shvi'it בתלוש ליתא במחובר איתא.
be-talush leita be-mechubar ita. שביעית Shvi'it doesn't apply to things that are
separated from the ground, now the קדושה kedusha of שביעית shvi'it does,
but the prohibition of מלאכה melacha is only on the ground. So
by שבת shabbat מלאכה melacha applies to a larger scope of things
whether they're growing from the ground or not, and by שביעית shvi'it
the prohibition of מלאכה melacha only applies to the things that are
growing from the ground right now. So therefore שבת shabbat is גדול
gadol in the sense that it is big, a big category bigger
than שביעית. shvi'it.
Now one minute. And the punishment of שביעית shviis is bigger than
מן המעשר. min ha-maaser. Now that's why it says גדול בשבת. gadol
ba-Shabbat. Now why does it say גדול בשביעית? gadol ba-shviit? Because שביעית
shviis is bigger than something else. וגדול ענשו של שביעית יותר מן
המעשר. ve-gadol onsho shel shviis yoser min ha-maaser. And the punishment of
שביעית shviis is, funny he uses the word punishment, but here it
really means like the scope of שביעית shviis is bigger than מעשר.
maaser. So שביעית shviis is גדול gadol relative to מעשר. maaser. Why?
דשביעית איתא בין במאכל אדם בין במאכל בהמה. de-shviis isa bein be-maachal
adam bein be-maachal beheima. שביעית shviis applies whether to things that are
eaten by people or things that are eaten by animals. ואילו מעשר
במאכל אדם איתא במאכל בהמה ליתא. ve-ilu maaser be-maachal adam isa be-maachal
beheima leisa.
מעשר maaser only applies to things that are eaten by people, not
that are eaten by animals. Okay, we will take a look in
a minute, it's going to quote the משנה mishna by שביעית, shviis,
so you will see that issue. Okay, because basically by שביעית shviis
also applies, first of all the פסוק pasuk by שביעית shviis says
ולבהמתך ולחיה אשר בארצך. ve-livhemtecha ve-lachaya asher be-artzecha.
Right, so since the food of שביעית shviis
and the קדושה kedusha applies to leaving the food over for the
animals, the קדושה kedusha of שביעית shviis applies even to things that
are just animal food. Whereas מעשר, maaser, it only applies to things
that are human food. Actually רש"י Rashi points out that biblically מעשר,
maaser, according to רש"י, Rashi, it's a little debate in the ראשונים,
rishonim, but anyway מעשר maaser
is only by דגן תירוש ויצהר, dagan tirosh ve-yitzhar, which is grain,
תירוש tirosh is wine, and יצהר yitzhar is oil. So it doesn't
even apply to all things. It doesn't apply to fruits, it doesn't
apply to vegetables biblically, only to, I mean it applies to grapes
and olives, but other than those, only grain, wine, and oil. But
דרבנן derabbanan it applies to all things that grow, even fruits and
vegetables, but only things that are edible by humans. So that way
שביעית shviis is גדול gadol in that the קדושה kedusha of שביעית
shviis applies to even animal food, whereas the קדושה kedusha of מעשר
maaser only to human food. So that's why it says גדול בשביעית
gadol ba-shviit relative to מעשר. maaser. ובר קפרא דתני כלל גדול. u-Var
Kappara de-tani klal gadol. So now we said all of this to
help us explain why בר קפרא Bar Kappara uses the phrase כלל
גדול. klal gadol. Because what's מעשר maaser גדול gadol about? So because
כלל גדול במעשר גדול ענשו של מעשר יותר משל פאה. klal gadol
be-maaser gadol onsho shel maaser yoser mi-shel peah. The punishment, or again
the scope of מעשר maaser is bigger than that of
פאה, peah, the leaving of the corner of the field. דאילו מעשר
איתא בתאנה וירק. de-ilu maaser isa be-te'eina ve-yerek. מעשר maaser applies to
figs and vegetables, why not, it's human food, it grows from the
ground. ואילו פאה ליתא בתאנה וירק. ve-ilu peah leisa be-te'eina ve-yerek. פאה
peah doesn't apply to figs and vegetables. Why not? דתנן כלל אמרו
בפאה. de-tanan klal amru be-peah. Because we talked כלל אמרו בפאה, klal
amru be-peah, they said a כלל, klal, notice no גדול, gadol, כל
שהוא אוכל ונשמר וגידולו מן הארץ, kol she-hu ochel ve-nishmar ve-gidulo min
ha-aretz, anything that is food and guarded, meaning it's not הפקר, hefker,
and grows from the ground, ולקיטתו כאחד, u-lekitaso ke-echad, and it's all
gathered as one, ומכניסו לקיום, u-machniso le-kiyum, and it actually can be
preserved rather than that it rots very quickly, חייב בפאה. chayav be-peah.
So that's obligated in פאה. peah. So by adding criteria you understand
you're shrinking the scope, right? The more criteria you have, the smaller
the scope. More things fit those criteria. So by פאה, peah, the
last two things are specific פאה peah criteria. לקיטתו כאחד, lekitaso ke-echad,
it's all harvested at one time, and מכניסו לקיום, machniso le-kiyum, that
it lasts, that it can be put away for storage. Those do
not apply by מעשר. maaser. And therefore the scope of פאה peah
is smaller than the scope of מעשר. maaser. So now we're going
to go explain all of these, one minute. So אוכל, ochel, food,
למעוטי ספיחי סטין le-mauti sefichai satin to exclude these various types of
wild growths of various plants, וקוצה, ve-kotza, and other types of like
thorns, I don't know how they translate, what English do they give
for that? Isatis tinctoria?
Woad plants, madder?
Whatever. Anyway, these things are either animal food and/or they are also
used for dyes. And שביעית shviis applies to animal food and things
that are used for dyes, but this does not apply to מעשר
maaser and does not apply to פאה. peah. Okay, so this would
apply for animal food because by מעשר maaser and שביעית, shviis, שביעית
shviis is animal food and dyes as well as human food, but
starting with מעשר maaser and פאה, peah, it's only human food. So
it excludes these things. ונשמר, ve-nishmar, and only things that are guarded,
למעוטי הפקר, le-mauti hefker, to exclude things that are just הפקר, hefker,
that are not guarded, that are grown wild. וגידולו מן הארץ, ve-gidulo
min ha-aretz, grows from the ground, למעוטי כמיהין ופטריות, le-mauti kmeihin u-pitriyos,
to exclude fungi and mushrooms because although those grow on the ground,
they don't grow from the ground, they're fungus. ולקיטתו כאחד. u-lekitaso ke-echad.
So all of that is the same by מעשר. maaser. So on
the one hand מעשר maaser is smaller than שביעית, shviis, it doesn't
apply to animal food or dyes. But now these first three is
מעשר maaser as well, basically human food that is guarded and protected
and grows from the ground. Now we add two criteria that are
unique to פאה. peah.
ולקיטתו כאחד, u-lekitaso ke-echad, it's harvested at one time, למעוטי תאנה, le-mauti
te'eina, to exclude figs. Apparently figs you harvest at various times throughout
the year. I don't know, you also do by olives? Maybe.
Almonds get the, you know, ripe first and
then but are they roughly at the same time or literally throughout
the year? I think olives grow throughout the year. Right. Yeah. Anyway,
yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, this does not just mean over a few
weeks, it means literally at various times throughout the year. ומכניסו לקיום
U'machniso l'kiyum and you can store it, למעוטי ירק lim'utei yerek to
exclude vegetables. Vegetables can't be stored because you know they don't last
a long time as opposed to grains. ואילו גבי מעשר תנן, v'ilu
gabi ma'aser tnan, by מעשר ma'aser you only have the first three
criteria. כלל אמרו במעשר, klal amru b'ma'aser, they said a כלל klal
according to Bar Kappara, כלל גדול, klal gadol, כל שהוא אוכל ונשמר
kol shehu ochel v'nishmar anything that is food and protected וגידולו מן
הארץ v'gidulo min ha'aretz and grows from the ground, חייב במעשר. chayav
b'ma'aser. ואילו לקיטתו כאחד ומכניסו לקיום, v'ilu likitato k'echad u'machniso l'kiyum, the
last two criteria, לא תנן lo tnan are not there, so that's
why Bar Kappara could call it גדול gadol because it has bigger
scope, מעשר ma'aser than פאה. pe'ah. Now תוספות Tosafot points out interestingly,
why is it since as I just told you מעשר ma'aser was
rabbinically extended to fruits and vegetables, biblically not, and פאה pe'ah also
תוספות Tosafot says it's the same type of an idea of rabbinically
extended them to all types of things like fruits and vegetables, why
did they give, why was פאה pe'ah smaller scope than מעשר? ma'aser?
Why did they decide to add these two criteria of harvested at
one time and can be preserved more by פאה pe'ah than by
מעשר? ma'aser? And תוספות Tosafot says because פאה pe'ah is the עניים
aniyim have to be waiting as you're harvesting, right, they have to
be sort of there hovering around waiting for you to harvest like
you see by Ruth. It's not like מעשר עני ma'aser ani where
you do the whole thing and after you're all done, you take
a tenth and you distribute it. There they are, they're sort of
like hovering around. So if you're not harvesting all at the same
time, then it's very you know not productive for them, right, they'll
be waiting and waiting and waiting and this week I'm only doing
a little bit and the rest I'll do a month from now,
whatever. So now maybe so the rabbis sort of felt it wasn't
in their best interest to say פאה pe'ah because they'll be, it
won't be you know the best way to spend their time. They'll
still do it because they'll hope to whatever, but therefore they figured
it would not make sense. Similarly by the fact that would the
food be able to be preserved, he says if you get a
lot of vegetables and it's all going to rot very quickly, again
they felt that people would, the עניים aniyim would you know not
would be waiting and hovering and spending their time and hoping for
it and in the end it would not ultimately be in their
best financial interest. So that's an interesting way, like you know it's
a little paternalistic, but it also could be a little realistic you
know that if and therefore that's why they have a smaller scope
for פאה. pe'ah. But again the גמרא Gemara explains in a very
sort of you know sort of non-central way that the גדול gadol
means that this scope of this is bigger than the scope of
something else. But what it really is encouraging us to do is
to compare things, on the one hand to compare שביעית, shevi'it, מעשר,
ma'aser, and פאה pe'ah about how broad of a scope, you know
שביעית shevi'it is a bigger scope,
מעשר ma'aser a little smaller, פאה pe'ah even smaller. The difference between
פאה pe'ah and מעשר ma'aser as I said תוספות Tosafot says has
to do with the fact that the עניים aniyim are hovering around.
The difference between שביעית shevi'it and מעשר ma'aser is presumably שביעית shevi'it
is much broader, you know it's קדושת הארץ kedushat ha'aretz so it
applies on a much broader scope of things that grow from the
ground and it goes to the בהמה beheimah and so on. And
then to compare also שביעית shevi'it and שבת Shabbat that they're both
איסור מלאכה, issur melacha, they're both seventh, seventh perek, seventh year, seventh
day. They both say כלל גדול klal gadol and they both have
interestingly אבות ותולדות. avot v'toladot. So by making that lineup it does
although again different scope שבת Shabbat is not just about land, שביעית
shevi'it is a מלאכה melacha concept but a מלאכה melacha about the
land. So it's actually quite a nice little opening that by raising
this question of גדול gadol makes us sort of compare these different
types of topics. Yeah.
Two quick questions. So is there any other place where it says
גדול gadol other than these over here?
ואהבת לרעך כמוך זה כלל גדול בתורה. V'ahavta l'rei'acha kamocha zeh klal
gadol ba'torah.
No, no, in the משנה. Mishnah. In the משנה? Mishnah?
Good question.
What?
In the משנה? Mishnah?
קידוש גדול? Kiddush gadol?
Yeah, I don't know I'd have to check.
Another question is why don't we just say גדול gadol means חשוב?
chashuv?
I mean yeah like I said the opening סוגיא sugya of a
מסכת masechet normally asks these questions which have relatively trivial questions you
know could have different types of answers but sometimes they're done more
you know it's a good question only if you have a good
answer for it. So okay yes Charlie.
There's a similar discussion in מסכת פאה masechet Pe'ah on comparing פאה
pe'ah to מעשר ma'aser and how it differs in source but they
don't use the word גדול. gadol. Right.
Right. So there you go. So it's very much I sort of
see this as also indicative that the גמרא Gemara understands that we're
in sort of
like a new type of like a new beginning of the מסכת.
masechet. You're saying the question is more to really get the ball
rolling?
I think so. Okay now the גמרא Gemara now the גמרא Gemara
gets to the heart of it. Okay this issue of
forgetting the existence of שבת. Shabbat. So let's take a look. רב
ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav u'Shmuel d'amri tarveihu, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
both say מתניתין בתינוק שנשבה לבין הנכרים וגר שנתגייר לבין הנכרים. matnitin
b'tinok shenishba l'vein hanachrim v'ger shenitgayer l'vein hanachrim. Our case that you
forgot שבת Shabbat existed really means you never knew שבת Shabbat existed.
It really means that you either were that this person was taken
captive as an infant and raised amongst non-Jews and never knew that
he or she was Jewish, or that he converted he or she
converted amongst non-Jews and never knew of the existence of שבת. Shabbat.
So our משנה Mishnah is talking about the fact that there is
that the person never knew of שבת. Shabbat. אבל הכיר ולבסוף שכח,
Aval hekir u'levasof shachach, but if you knew there was שבת Shabbat
and then you forgot about שבת, Shabbat, then if you can imagine
that that would be possible,
then... but if you knew and that you forgot, well you'd make
it as if each week you forgot that this week was שבת
Shabbat because at once you knew, and maybe it's also because we
sort of don't, you know, sort of also don't accept the idea
that you can, I mean we believe it can happen, but somehow
הלכתית, halachicly, legally, we're not prepared to sort of to, you know,
acknowledge that you completely forgot about שבת. Shabbat. So we translate it
as forgetting each week that this is שבת. Shabbat. So this is
going to be the focus of the גמרא Gemara about whether this,
a, whether if somebody never knew, are they still liable for once
an offering? That's partly what רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel are saying,
that even if you never knew, you're liable once an offering. And
number two, if you knew and forgot, does that make you liable
for every שבת, Shabbat, more liable? Now, before we get to that,
and that's very important because it also touches on this big idea
that started with the רמב״ם Rambam broadening this concept of תינוק שנשבה
tinok shenishba and has a lot of relevance nowadays, I do want
to point out a very important תוספות, Tosafot, גר שנתגייר בין הנכרים,
Ger shenitgayyer bein hanokhrim, one line in תוספות Tosafot very bottom of
the page. בפני ג׳, Bifnei gimel, first of all it can't mean
totally amongst non-Jews, there has to have been a בית דין. Beit
Din. ולו, now okay fine, so there was a passing a בית
דין Beit Din, passing through and this person converted. But and they
never knew about שבת. Shabbat. But תוספות Tosafot says wait a minute,
if there's a בית דין, Beis Din what do you mean they
never knew about שבת? Shabbat? Aren't you supposed to tell the person
the מצוות mitzvot and isn't he supposed to accept the מצוות? mitzvot?
So it says ולא הודיעו מצוות שבת. V'lo hodiu mitzvot Shabbat. They
oh they forgot, amongst the מצוות mitzvot they were telling him they
never got around to mention שבת. Shabbat. דאי נתגייר בין לבין עצמו
לא הוי גר. De-i nitgayyer bein l'vein atzmo lo havai ger. If
he was by himself he wouldn't be a גר. ger. And this
leads to an extremely important principle about גירות, geirut, which is that
בדיעבד bedi'avad if you do not inform somebody about the מצוות, mitzvot,
it is not מעכב. me'akeiv. Now,
because I mean you could say, well if you don't inform them
about, you know, you have to inform them about some of the
מצוות, mitzvot, but again the fact that you're not informing them about
שבת Shabbat makes it seem like pretty big. Now, that's not to
be confused with the idea that if they don't do קבלת מצוות
kabbalat mitzvot it's not מעכב. me'akeiv. Somebody, it's like signing a blank
check, you know, you could say I accept the מצוות mitzvot whatever
they are. I have no idea, nobody told me what the מצוות
mitzvot were, you know, but I accept them. Whatever, exactly, like נעשה
ונשמע. na'aseh v'nishma. I accept them whatever they are. So there's, you
know, the discussion about קבלת מצוות kabbalat mitzvot is a different discussion.
But primarily based on this גמרא, Gemara, you know, and one or
two others, you know, becomes the position that בדיעבד bedi'avad
without specifying the מצוות mitzvot you could still have גירות. geirut. But
what do you mean this guy never knew? Didn't they know at
the time of גירות? geirut? No, they didn't tell him at the
time of גירות. geirut. Yes.
For the מצוות mitzvot that we're that they're supposed to be taught
to a convert according to מסכת יבמות Masechet Yevamot are פאה לקט
ושכחה. peah leket v'shikchah.
No, it says you start with that. But then it says, you
know, you talk about עד שלא באת למדה זו חיללת שבת אי
אתה חייב סקילה, Ad shelo bata l'middah zu chillalta Shabbat ee ata
chayyav sekilah,
so it mentions שבת Shabbat there. It starts with פאה לקט ושכחה.
peah leket v'shikchah. Okay. But now we're getting to this idea that
they're saying that our משנה's Mishna's talking that you never knew. Now
I want to say something about that as well. The, well you
know what, I'll hold off about that because we'll see a debate
about it. Okay. So there's two points: one if you never knew
you bring a חטאת, chatat, and the other is if you knew
and forgot, that's like forgetting each שבת. Shabbat.
So you need to bring one one for each שבת.
Shabbat. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. תנן, Tnan, now
we're going to try to prove it or disprove it. Let's look
at our
משנה. Mishna. השוכח עיקר שבת, Hashoche'ach ikar Shabbat, that if you forgot
the שבת Shabbat existed. Now it says השוכח, Hashoche'ach, you forgot. לאו
מכלל דהוה ליה ידיעה מעיקרא? Lav miklal d'havai lei yedi'ah me'ikara? Doesn't
that suggest that you originally knew? And they would say that no
if you originally knew it's worse. מה, Ma, no. מאי כל השוכח
עיקר שבת? Mai kol hashoche'ach ikar Shabbat? What does it mean that
you forgot the basis of שבת, Shabbat, you know, the existence of
שבת? Shabbat? דהויא שכוחה ממנו עיקרה של שבת. D'havai shechuchah mimenu ikara
shel Shabbat. It was always forgotten from you, meaning unknown to you,
the existence of שבת. Shabbat. It is weak. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: אבל, Aval, said the גמרא, Gemara, fine. הכיר
ולסוף שכח מאי? Hikir u'lesof shachach mai? So what do you want
to say though? If you actually knew and then forgot, what would
be the הלכה? halachah? חייב על כל שבת ושבת? Chayyav al kol
shabbat v'shabbat? Do you then say you're חייב chayyav on each שבת?
Shabbat? דתניא היודע עיקר שבת ועשה מלאכות הרבה בשבתות הרבה חייב על
כל שבת ושבת. D'tanya hayode'a ikar Shabbat v'asah melachot harbeh b'shabbatot harbeh
chayyav al kol shabbat v'shabbat. The next line in the משנה Mishna
goes on and says that if you knew שבת Shabbat and you
forgot the day of the week, you forgot which day was שבת,
Shabbat, that's when you're חייב chayyav on each שבת. Shabbat. So according
to you, it should have said a bigger חידוש. chiddush. It should
have said that even if you forgot the existence of שבת Shabbat
altogether, you're חייב chayyav on every day of the week. ליתני, Lisni,
according to that, it should say explicitly היכא דבסוף שכח, Heicha d'bisof
shachach, that even if you completely forgot about שבת Shabbat that you're
חייב chayyav for that you would be חייב chayyav for each שבת.
Shabbat. וכל שכן הא, V'chol sheken ha,
and certainly in a case where you would forgot, you know, where
you knew about the existence of שבת Shabbat and you just forgot
each week that it was שבת. Shabbat.
מאי היודע, Mai hayode'a, so the גמרא Gemara says no. It's going
to the same way we re-translated the first line in the משנה,
Mishna, that it says when it says you forgot שבת Shabbat it
means you never knew שבת, Shabbat, it's going to re-translate the second
line in the משנה. Mishna. מאי היודע עיקר שבת? Mai hayode'a ikar
Shabbat? What does it mean you knew there was שבת Shabbat and
then you forgot the day of the week? It doesn't mean you
forgot the day of the week. מי שהיה יודע עיקרה של שבת
ושכחה. Mi shehayah yode'a ikara shel Shabbat v'shechechah. So basically it's like
the domino. The first
line... אבל לא שכחה. aval lo shikhacha. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so what are you telling me? If you didn't forget the existence
of שבת, Shabbat, מאי, mai, then what would you say? חייב אכל
מלאכה ומלאכה, chayav a-kol melachah u'melachah, right where we're assuming it's like
this domino effect. I don't know if it's sort of, I wish
I had, I should have had a pen, right? Or do we
have markers here? There's
markers. My eraser, where's my eraser? Look at that, I just feel
like it's getting a little, maybe I have to write on the
board.
So the משנה Mishnah says, right, if you forgot the existence, existence
of שבת, Shabbat, it says you bring one. Forget that today was
שבת, Shabbat,
you bring one per שבת, Shabbat, right?
So that's what our משנה Mishnah says, right? And if you forgot
the
מלאכה melachah or מלאכות, melachot, you bring one per each מלאכה. melachah.
That's our משנה. Mishnah. So רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel come and
say that what they say is, if you never knew what was
שבת, Shabbat, it was one. Right? So רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel,
I
don't have a
pen next to it, yeah, I'll just write it like inserted. Never
knew, they say it was one. So the גמרא, Gemara, and if
you forgot the existence, then it's one per שבת. Shabbat. So the
גמרא Gemara assumes that if you forgot today was שבת, Shabbat, right,
it's one per מלאכה, melachah, it assumes that everything gets more severe.
So they say, but what do you do with the language of
the משנה? Mishnah? So they re-interpret each phrase to mean the next
phrase. Forgot the existence of שבת Shabbat means you forgot today was
שבת. Shabbat. Forgot today was שבת Shabbat means that you, that you,
that you
forgot, forget the existence
means you never knew.
Forgot, I'm sorry, sorry, you're right. Forgot the existence means you never
knew. Forgot today was שבת Shabbat means you forgot the existence of
שבת, Shabbat, right? So we're constantly, they're assuming everything is one level
more severe, so we're re-interpreting every line of the משנה. Mishnah.
What?
Well, it's going to get to it. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אבל לא שכח מאי? aval lo shakhach mai? If you
did not forget
that, that, that the existence of שבת, Shabbat, you knew the existence,
you just forgot that today was שבת. Shabbat. So if we would
have to upgrade everything, what would we say there? We'd say חייב
אכל מלאכה ומלאכה, chayav a-kol melachah u'melachah, then you'd say you're חייב
chayav for each מלאכה, melachah, עד דתני היודע שהוא שבת ועשה מלאכות
הרבה בשבתות הרבה חייב על כל מלאכה ומלאכה. ad d'tani hayodeya shehu
Shabbat v'asah melachot harbeh b'shabbatot harbeh chayav al kol melachah u'melachah. There
the משנה Mishnah is explicit, you know it's שבת Shabbat and you
do מלאכות, melachot, you're חייב chayav for each מלאכה. melachah. So according
to you, everything is upgraded, ליתני היודע עיקר שבת. litni hayodeya ikar
Shabbat. Tell me just the case that you knew about the existence
of שבת Shabbat but you forgot that today was, וכל שכן הא,
v'kol sheken ha, and certainly that. And this phrase you can't re-interpret.
Forgetting the existence of שבת, Shabbat, you could say means you never
knew. Forgetting today was שבת Shabbat means that you forgot the existence
of שבת. Shabbat. It's all about forgetting שבת. Shabbat. But when you
get to this phrase, you forgot the מלאכה, melachah, you can't say
that means you forgot today was שבת. Shabbat. There's no way to
re-interpret this phrase. So if we're re-interpreting the whole משנה Mishnah and
re-interpreting each phrase one higher, you get stuck over here.
What, can you say you forgot that there are מלאכות? melachot?
Are מלאכות? melachot? Maybe. Anyway, thankfully, the גמרא Gemara isn't doing that.
So the גמרא Gemara says fine, let's rephrase. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אלא מתניתין כשיטה דשכח כך. ela matnitin k'shita d'shachach
kach. You're right, we're not going to debate the simple sense of
the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah is, you knew and you forgot
the existence of שבת, Shabbat, that's one חטאת. chatat. That would not
be multiple. So we remove the idea of רב Rav and שמואל
Shmuel that knowing שבת Shabbat and forgetting about it becomes as if
you forgot each week. That case as well is only one חטאת.
chatat. You knew the existence, you forgot about the existence of שבת,
Shabbat, it's one big mistake, it's one חטאת. chatat. That they agree
to. And the rest of the משנה Mishnah reads the simple way.
והכי איתמר דרב ושמואל, v'hakhi itmar d'Rav u'Shmuel, and here's what they're
really saying, דאמרי תרווייהו, d'amri tarvaihu, here's what was said. רב Rav
and שמואל Shmuel both say,
אפילו, afilu, not only, but אפילו, afilu, תינוק שנשבה בין הנכרים וגר
שנתגייר בין הנכרים, tinok she'nishba bein ha'nochrim v'ger she'nitgayer bein ha'nochrim, even
if you never knew about שבת Shabbat in your life, that the
guy was, the infant was taken captive, כהיכרו בסוף שכח דמי וחייב.
k'hikro b'sof shachach dami v'chayav. That at least is like you knew
and forgot, and you bring one חטאת. chatat. So they're not saying
knowing and forgetting becomes like multiple forgettings and so on. That they
agree. You're right. Forgetting the existence of שבת, Shabbat, we're not going
to re-interpret the משנה. Mishnah. Forgetting the existence of שבת Shabbat is
only one, one big mistake. But the חידוש chidush is even never
knowing is also one. Okay? It's not just for, even, you could
say if you never knew you're totally blameless. No, even never knowing
is also, is also one חטאת chatat offering. That's what they say.
And that argues... Rabbi Yochanan and Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish both say
דוקא היכא דהוה ליה בסוף שפחה? davka heicha de'hava leh besof shifcha?
No, only if there's some
sort of fault.
Only if you knew about שבת Shabbat and forgot. But a תינוק
שנשבה בין הנכרים tinok shenishba bein ha'nochrim or a גר שנתגייר בין
הנכרים, ger shenitgayer bein ha'nochrim,
but an infant that was taken captive or somebody that converted and
never knew about שבת, Shabbat, פטור patur is completely exempt. Now if
you ask yourself, right, obviously Rabbi Yochanan and Resh Lakish make enormous
sense. How could you blame somebody, like what fault do they have
if they grew up without ever knowing that they were Jewish? Why
would they bring one sin offering? And the רמב"ם, Rambam, and this
becomes very important for contemporary application which I'll speak about in a
minute, says that, you know, in some place says that תינוק שנשבה
tinok shenishba is an אנוס. anuss. Of course he's an אנוס. anuss.
You know, he never knew. What could you expect from him? They
never knew he's Jewish. Sometimes you could say somebody didn't know but
they had a, like you know, ignorance of the law is no
excuse. They should have, you know, you can't say, oh, nobody ever
told me what the הלכות halachas were. You know you're Jewish, you
know about שבת, Shabbat, you should be learning the הלכות. halachas. Okay,
but if you never knew you're Jewish, clearly you're an אנוס, anuss,
there's no, there's no fault. So of course Rabbi Yochanan and Resh
Lakish make sense, and the רמב"ם Rambam says this when he winds
up applying this to be lenient about people that, you know, that
are non-observant. We'll talk about that in a minute.
So,
but what's the idea of רב ושמואל? Rav u'Shmuel? And so it
seems like their idea is not that they're claiming that the person
has fault or is negligent, but it seems like it's a concept
of a sin offering, that according to the גמרא, Gemara, the idea
that if you sinned you have to bring a קרבן korban is
not just because of personal guilt and to cleanse yourself. It also
does some function of cleansing the sin, that there's some idea that
there is some metaphysical rupture out there, you know, something bad that
has been created in the world, and this sin offering fixes it.
I'll give you another example. The beginning of the גמרא Gemara in
הוריות Horayot speaks about the fact that בית דין Beis Din ruled
in a certain way, I listened to them, I sinned, and then
they realized they made a mistake. So if half of כלל ישראל
Klal Yisrael listened to them, the בית דין Beis Din. brings a
קרבן. korban. But if less than a majority of כלל ישראל Klal
Yisrael listened to them, they don't bring a קרבן. korban. Who brings
the קרבן? korban? I do. Now why the heck do I bring
a קרבן? korban? They're the בית דין. I'm supposed to listen to
them. I'm not supposed to be smarter than they are, right? So
what I did was completely blameless, but at the end of the
day, I'm the one that did the sin. You know, somebody broke
it, somebody's got to pay for it. It doesn't matter that you're
to blame, you're not to blame, you're the one who did it,
you bring the חטאת chatas to fix it. So there is this
concept that again a חטאת chatas is not just about fault or
guilt, it's about something was broken and needs to be fixed. And
even if you're blameless, you're the one who did it, you have
to bring that sin offering. And that's the position of רב ושמואל.
Rav u'Shmuel. And interestingly, the רמב"ם Rambam rules like רב ושמואל. Rav
u'Shmuel. He says you have to bring one sin offering even if
you never knew you were Jewish. He says it's כשוגג, k'shogeg, like
a שוגג, shogeg, by which I take to mean not like there's
a little bit, not that there's somewhat negligence, but it means it's
the same category. It doesn't matter that you were faultless, what matters
is you did it, you bring a קרבן. korban. So I want
to, that's number one about understanding רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel. Yes.
What's the idea of an אנוס anuss in general?
So אונס רחמנא פטריה oness Rachmana patreih is where you are not
choosing, making a conscious choice and choosing on your own initiative to
do it. Like an אנוס anuss where somebody, you know, sort of
forced you, you know, sort of held a gun to your head
and made you light a candle on שבת. Shabbat. Or it's either
accidental like you tripped and you, like, hit a light switch which
is actually מתעסק, misasek, or it was not your will that was,
you know, that was sort of the reason behind this. Here, it's
your will, it's just you're blameless. So but there you own, here
you own the action more than if somebody's holding the gun to
your head, right? This is still your choice even though you're blameless.
Yes.
It seems to be as a contradiction or conflict between הוריות Horayot
where you described somebody's a part of the community, right, so they're
involved with that and they can bring the sin offering.
But the person
who doesn't know, he's not...
Right. If you remain ignorant, you're never going to bring a sin
offering. It must, at some time after 20 years, you know, your
parents track you down because you were taken captive as a baby
and they track you down and they find out and they tell
you that you really were born Jewish and so on.
So how many sin offerings does he then bring? One!
Just one. Exactly that. One for the basic according to רב ושמואל,
Rav u'Shmuel, one because it's like forgetting שבת Shabbat exists. It's sort
of like Cardinal Lustiger, right? So, what? Yeah, right? So did he
know, did he always know he was Jewish or he found out
later in life?
Anyway, I don't know. Okay, but that would be an example, right?
So you found out later in life and then what do you
do? All right, so let's read a little bit more and then
I want to talk about a little bit of the contemporary relevance
of this concept. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מיתיבי,
meitivei, I'll ask you on this. We have a ברייתא. braysa. כלל
גדול אמרו בשבת. Klal gadol amru ba'Shabbat. They told, again starting up
like our משנה, mishna, but you'll see it's more detailed about the
positions. A general principle, a big principle they said by שבת. Shabbat.
כל השוכח עיקר שבת, Kol hashocheiach ikar Shabbat, if you forget the
existence of שבת, Shabbat, ועשה מלאכות הרבה בשבתות הרבה, ve'asa melachos harbeh
be'Shabbatot harbeh, and you do many מלאכות, melachos, אינו חייב אלא אחת,
eino chayav ela achat, you only bring one. That sounds like our
משנה. mishna. משנה Mishna *Mishna* you knew שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat* and you
forgot about it. כיצד *Keitzad*? But now it gives an illustration. תינוק
שנשבה tinok shenishba? לבין הנכרים *Tinok shenishba levein hanachrim* וגר שנתגייר בין
הנכרים *veger shenitgayer bein hanachrim*. If an infant was taken captive or
a convert converted and amongst the non-Jews and never knew and then
totally never was informed about שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat* or never even knew
that they were Jews. The convert by the way you could say
has more responsibility. Knows he's Jewish, just is not in a place
where maybe he has access to enough
information, but at least you could in theory say should find out
more about what their Judaism means. But the infant case has no
knowledge of their Jewish identity, so again it's clearly a hundred percent
of an אונס ones, *oness*. Okay, and so therefore this is given
as the example of, and therefore what? ועשה מלאכות הרבה בשבתות הרבה
*ve'asah melachot harbeh beShabbatot harbeh*, did many מלאכות *melachot* over many different
שבתות *Shabbatot*, אינו חייב אלא חטאת chatas, אחת *eino chayav ela chatat
achat*. You only bring one חטאת chatas, *chatat* offering. Now, וחייב *vechayav*
for for all of your שבת *Shabbat* violations your entire life until
you remember that you're Jewish or were informed. וחייב על הדם *vechayav
al hadam*, let's say you've been eating blood, that's what you do
every Tuesdays, you have some blood. So anyway, so you do this
for your entire life, אחת *achat*, it's only one חטאת chatas, *chatat*
offering for all the different violations. ועל החלב אחת *ve'al hachelev achat*,
all the different times you ate חלב *chelev*, one חטאת chatas, *chatat*
offering, that's on Wednesdays. ועל עבודה זרה avoda zara, אחת *ve'al avoda
zara achat*, עבודה זרה avoda zara *avoda zara* one חטאת chatas. *chatat*
offering. So basically there are thirty-six types of עבירות *averot* that you
bring a חטאת chatas? *chatat* for. Okay, so this person, he could
have done every single עבירה *avera* in the book, without knowing they're
Jewish, they would only bring max thirty-six חטאות *chata'ot*, only one for
each different, that's a lot. How many people are regularly doing well
depends, at that time עבודה זרה avoda zara. *avoda zara* yes, but
there's a lot of things you wouldn't do
anyway even if you didn't know you were Jewish. But yeah, that's
the wait a minute, that's the position of the חכמים *chachamim*, like
רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rebbi Yochanan veReish Lakish, *Rabbi Yochanan Reish Lakish*,
which is I'm sorry, like רב ושמואל Rav uShmuel *Rav and Shmuel*,
which is one per category, per category, even if you never knew.
ומונבז פוטר *umunbaz poter*, מונבז Munbaz *Munbaz* would exempt. וכך היה מונבז
Munbaz דן לפני רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva, *vechach haya Munbaz dan lifnei
Rabbi Akiva*, and here's how מונבז Munbaz *Munbaz* would sort of argue
his case in front of רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*, because
presumably רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* was the first position that
said that you are obligated even if you never knew. So he
said like this, listen. הלא מזיד meizid. קרי חוטא chotei *halo mazed
kari chotei*, מזיד meizid. *mazed* is called the חוטא *chotei*. In one
place in the תורה Torah *Torah* it says, normally חוטא *chotei* is
used by a inadvertent sinner because חוטא *chotei* also like the רמב"ן
*Ramban* says means like to miss the target. It's not like a
willful sin, it's to do something off even though it's not ideally
what you wanted to do, there's negligence and so on. But there's
one place the תורה *Torah* calls a מזיד meizid *mazed* a חוטא
*chotei*. ושוגג קרי חוטא *veshogeg kari chotei*, and a שוגג shogeg *shogeg*
is called a חוטא *chotei*. So מה מזיד meizid, היתה לו ידיעה
אף שוגג shogeg היתה לו ידיעה *ma mazed hayta lo yedi'ah af
shogeg hayta lo yedi'ah*. There has to be some degree of blame,
some degree of fault by the שוגג shogeg *shogeg*. So therefore this
guy that never knew, you cannot be obligated a חטאת chatas. *chatat*.
That's what מונבז Munbaz. *Munbaz* says. So exactly this debate, רב ושמואל
Rav uShmuel, *Rav and Shmuel* on one side and רבי יוחנן וריש
לקיש Rebbi Yochanan veReish Lakish *Rabbi Yochanan Reish Lakish* on the other
is the debate of רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and מונבז Munbaz? *Munbaz*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, but let's see now what רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says back. So he says, שוגג shogeg *shogeg* has
to have some knowledge. So מה מזיד meizid היתה לו ידיעה אף
שוגג shogeg היתה לו ידיעה *ma mazed hayta lo yedi'ah af shogeg
hayta lo yedi'ah*. Somebody who never knew isn't a שוגג shogeg *shogeg*.
אמר לו רבי עקיבא *amar lo Rabbi Akiva*, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
said, הריני מוסיף על דבריך *hareni mosif al devarecha*, let me go
ahead and take your line of reasoning one step further. He's going
to do a reductio ad absurdum. אם מה מזיד meizid היתה לו
ידיעה בשעת מעשה *im ma mazed hayta lo yedi'ah besha'at ma'aseh*, מזיד
meizid? *mazed* not only knew at the outset but even when the
מזיד meizid. *mazed* person was violating they knew they were violating. So
if you want to compare a שוגג shogeg *shogeg* to a מזיד
meizid, *mazed*, don't just say that you have to know originally, say
it has to be like a מזיד meizid. *mazed*, אף שוגג shogeg,
שהיתה לו ידיעה בשעת מעשה *af shogeg shehayta lo yedi'ah besha'at ma'aseh*.
So a שוגג *shogeg* also somebody that knows at the moment of
violation that he's violating, right? So that's obviously absurd. So he said,
if you want to really make a שוגג *shogeg* like a מזיד
meizid, *mazed*, you'll turn him into a מזיד mezid *mazed*. אמר לו
*amar lo*, הן *hen*, yes, וכל שכן שהוספת *vechol sheken she'osafta*, and
that was good that you now expanded the category. So basically he's
saying, one man's reductio ad absurdum is another man's אין הכי נמי
*ein hachi nami*. So he said, you think that's an absurd, I
agree with you, there are times you could even know at the
moment that you're violating and still be called a שוגג *shogeg* and
still bring a חטאת chatas *chatat* offering. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
going to have to figure out what that is because that to
us sounds like a מזיד mezid *mazed*.
But anyway, אמר לו *amar lo*, he said back to him, לדבריך
אין זה קרוי שוגג אלא מזיד *ledevarecha ein zeh karui shogeg ela
mazed*, what you talking about? If the person knows at the time
they're violating, that's not a שוגג *shogeg*, that's a מזיד *mazed*. So
that's the debate of רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and מונבז Munbaz *Munbaz*.
But basically מונבז Munbaz *Munbaz* is saying if you don't have some
knowledge at one time that this was wrong, you don't have to
bring a קרבן korban *korban*, and רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says even
if you're always completely ignorant. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says קתני
מיהא *katani miha*, we teach nevertheless, כיצד *keitzad*, what's an example of
one חטאת chatas. *chatat* offering and forgetting, תינוק *tinok*, the example of
תינוק *tinok* of never knowing. בשלמא לרב ושמואל ניחא *bishlama lerav ushmuel
nicha*, according to רב ושמואל Rav uShmuel, *Rav and Shmuel* we understand,
they're the major position of this ברייתא braita, *braita*, they're the רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* position, that even if you never knew, you bring
one
חטאת Chatat, *chatat* offering. אלא לרבי יוחנן ולשמעון לקיש *ela lerabbi yochanan
uleshimon lakish*, according to רבי יוחנן ולשמעון לקיש *Rabbi Yochanan and Shimon
Lakish* אמר לך רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש, Rebbi Yochanan veReish Lakish רבי
יוחנן וריש לקיש Rebbi Yochanan veReish Lakish would say to you, לא
מי איכא מונבז דפטר? Lo mi ika Munbaz depatar? Okay, we don't
go like the רבי עקיבא, we don't go like the תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. There's a מונבז Munbaz here, there's another opinion that says
that if you never knew you're exempt, ואנן דאמרינן כמונבז, veanan deamrinan
keMunbaz, we go like מונבז Munbaz now. If you want to go
like a דעת יחיד daat yachid and you have to choose between,
you know, say מונבז Munbaz who we will almost never hear about
again against רבי עקיבא and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is not
a very strong backing of your position, but obviously they were persuaded
by the argument. You know, they felt if somebody never knew, how
could you say they have to bring a sin offering? So the
debate of if somebody never knew do you bring a חטאת, Chatat.
תינוק שנשבה? tinok shenishba רב ושמואל Rav uShmuel. says you bring one
sin offering. רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש says no, you don't bring any,
it's the debate of רבי עקיבא and מונבז. Munbaz Let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara what it says a little bit about
this debate.
מאי טעמא דמונבז, Mai taama deMunbaz, what's the reasoning of מונבז? It's
interesting, right? We would have said what's the reasoning of רב Rav
ושמואל, what's the reasoning again, no fault you're still bringing a sin
offering.
Wasn't ריש לקיש Reish Lakish one of the in one of those
categories?
Well, he didn't, he grew up as a bandit. I don't think
he grew up not knowing he was Jewish.
But he wasn't keeping,
right, he wasn't observing, right. I don't know if that was exactly
תינוק שנשבה tinok she'nishba, plus he was an adult too, except right,
maybe, it's interesting, maybe. Okay, so anyway, we would have said what's
the reason of רב ושמואל, right? We would have said, you know,
if you had no fault why are you bringing? But again as
I said, I think the גמרא's Gemara concept of חטאת, you also
see this a lot by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right? By יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, the purpose of the עבודת יום הכיפורים avodas Yom
HaKippurim is וכיפר על הקודש, vechiper al hakodesh, to purify the sanctuary.
It also mentions at the end that the שעיר המשתלח seir hamishtaleiach
purifies the sins of בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, but the basic idea
of the fundamental עבודה avoda is done because somehow the sin has
impurified the מקדש Mikdash and you have to cleanse it. So the
idea that you did a sin you bring a קרבן even if
you have no fault, that's רב ושמואל. We want to understand what's
the reason of מונבז or רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש that say you're
exempt. So we already learned in the משנה that he links it,
he links שוגג and מזיד. Let's see what the ברייתא, let's see
what the גמרא Gemara, does. מאי טעמא דמונבז? Mai taama deMunbaz? דכתיב
Dechtiv תורה אחת יהיה לכם לעושה בשגגה. Torah achas yihiyeh lachem laoseh
bishgaga. So here is where we're just spelling out the linking of
שוגג and מזיד. One rule you should have for you for those
who do in error. וסמיך ליה והנפש אשר תעשה ביד רמה, Usamich
lei vehanefesh asher taaseh beyad rama, somebody who does with an outstretched
hand את השם הוא מגדף es Hashem hu megadef and this person
is חייב כרת. chayav kares. This is about cursing God. הקיש שוגג
למזיד, Heikish shogeg lemeizid, so it juxtaposes the שוגג case to the
מזיד case. מה מזיד דאית ליה ידיעה אף שוגג דאית ליה ידיעה.
Mah meizid deis lei yedia af shogeg deis lei yedia. Pretty similar
to what מונבז said, except מונבז used the word חוטא and here
it's doing it by juxtaposition. But it juxtaposes a שוגג בשגגה shogeg
bishgaga to יד רמה, yad rama, to מזיד, and it says the
same way מזיד there was some knowledge, מזיד was knowledge from the
beginning to end, but there was an idea of knowledge, even שוגג
you had to have initially some awareness that it was forbidden, even
if now you've forgotten it. לרבנן, Lerabanan, the rabbis, האי תורה אחת
מאי עבדי ליה? hai Torah achas mai avdi lei? What do they
do with that, with the fact that it links שוגג to מזיד?
מיבעי ליה
לכדמקרי ליה רבי יהושע בן לוי לבריה, Mibai lei lechidemakri lei Rebbi
Yehoshua ben Levi levrei, like רבי יהושע בן לוי Rebbi Yehoshua ben
Levi read to his son when he read this פסוק. pasuk. תורה
אחת יהיה לכם לעושה בשגגה, Torah achas yihiyeh lachem laoseh bishgaga, it
says one rule for you who do in error. וכתיב וכי תשגו
ולא תעשו את כל המצוות האלה, Uchtiv vechi tishgu velo saasu es
kol hamitzvos haeleh, if you don't do all these מצוות, mitzvos, which
חז"ל Chazal understand means you do עבודה זרה, avoda zara. which is
כנגד keneged all the מצוות. mitzvos. So if you, if you do
עבודה זרה avoda zara. by mistake you bring a חטאת, and then
it juxtaposes to the שוגג and the חטאת, וכתיב
והנפש אשר תעשה ביד רמה, Uchtiv vehanefesh asher taaseh beyad rama, a
case of מזיד. So what's the purpose of this? הוקשו כולם לעבודה
זרה, Hukshu kulam laavoda zara, it's to link everything to the sin
of עבודה זרה. avoda zara, מה להלן דבר שחייבים על זדונו כרת
ובשגגתו חטאת, Mah lehallan davar shechayavim al zedono kares uvshigagaso chatas, because
it says what happens if you do with an outstretched arm, that
could either be read as the case of מגדף, megadef, of like
being מגדף megadef cursing God, or it could be read as a
case of עבודה זרה. avoda zara So the גמרא here
is
reading it as עבודה זרה. And what we're learning from this is
not that you need to have some knowledge by שוגג like by
מזיד, which is what מונבז does. What we're learning it to tell
you is the principle of when you bring a חטאת. When do
you bring a חטאת? When it is like this sin of עבודה
זרה, which is what? חייב כרת chayav kares as it tells you
by the case of מזיד. מה להלן דבר שחייב על זדונו כרת
ובשגגתו חטאת, Mah lehallan davar shechayav al zedono kares uvshigagaso chatas, the
same way by the עבודה זרה it tells you that if you
do it במזיד bemeizid it's כרת, kares, and from there we learn
that if it's בשוגג beshogeg you bring a חטאת. אף
כל דבר שחייב על זדונו כרת ובשגגתו חטאת. Af kol davar shechayav
al zedono kares uvshigagaso chatas. So that's true in general, you bring
a חטאת only for things you're חייב כרת. chayav kares. So again
what the תורה does is it juxtaposes מזיד, את השם הוא מגדף
ביד רמה, es Hashem hu megadef beyad rama, to a חטאת. discuss
what מונבז learns from it is, don't close the גמרא yet, I
want to say make a ברכו, Borchu, but מונבז learns from it
is the important principle of that you have to have some knowledge
even by שוגג, you have to have had at one point some
awareness, like מזיד always has awareness, and what we learn from it
is, no, the same way מזיד is כרת, karet, and that's juxtaposed
to חטאת, the only time you bring a sin offering is a
type of a sin that if you were to do it intentionally
you would get כרת, karet, like שבת. Now I want to say
something about this principle of תינוק שנשבה, tinok she'nishba. which is, in
this גמרא, it's all a very narrow discussion of do you bring
a sin offering. And interestingly, רמב"ם Rambam even rules like רב and
שמואל Shmuel that you bring a sin offering. Nevertheless, it provides an
important conceptual framework for the רמב"ם Rambam and then for later פוסקים
poskim to be lenient about people that were like not observant because
they had a different background. And it starts, so the רמב"ם Rambam
starts with the Karaites. The רמב"ם Rambam early in his early stage,
sort of life, was very antagonistic towards the Karaites, and basically said
אין להם חלק לעולם הבא, ein lahem chelek le'olam ha'ba, they don't
believe in עיקרי אמונה, ikrei emunah, all this type of stuff. And
then later in his life, actually interestingly, when he had more positive
interactions with a more positive group of Karaites, who were more polite
in terms of their relations to the rabbinic Jews, anyway, he basically
said, you know what, you can't really blame the Karaites for their
errors because they're like a תינוק שנשבה. tinok she'nishba They grew up
as Karaites and they were educated in this way, so even when
they learn there are other strands of Judaism and there's rabbinic Judaism,
they think we're wrong and they're right. So therefore, they cannot be
held responsible. They're like תינוק שנשבה tinok she'nishba because this is the
way they were educated and brought up. Now when the רמב"ם Rambam
says this, he only says it to sort of offset the most
harsh statements he says by Karaites, like basically like we have to
wish them dead and so on.
But later on in the בית יוסף, Beit Yosef, the שולחן ערוך,
Shulchan Aruch, he uses the רמב"ם Rambam for other areas as well,
and that normally when we would let's say exclude somebody because he
was a מחלל שבת, mechalel Shabbat, we shouldn't apply this to Karaites
who are only doing it because they have because they believe in,
they were brought up in a different way, and they're like a
תינוק שנשבה tinok she'nishba and they never understood that this was wrong.
And even though they see we see it's wrong, they believe that
we're the ones making the mistake. As you can see, this becomes
a helpful model and became a helpful model in the time of
modernity, when most of the Jewish people stopped observing שבת, to try
to say that they're not in this classic excluded category, they're all
in the תינוק שנשבה tinok she'nishba category. Of course, that works if
you were brought up not פרום, frum, and then you believe that
the פרום frum people don't know what they're talking about and that
really you're right and they're wrong. It was רב קוק Rav Kook
and others that extended it even to people that are brought up
פרום, frum, that says that nowadays like everybody is a תינוק שנשבה
tinok she'nishba, because of the influence of the larger society, which is
a little bit, obviously, on the one hand it's very nice and
it's very inclusive, but it's also deeply problematic in terms of the
fact that it's very patronizing. That even if you're brought up in
a certain way and you make a choice to accept or reject,
נעבעך, nebech, you really don't know what you're choosing because you're just
influenced by what everybody else is saying. But anyway, the effect of
that was to be much more inclusive and it primarily, initially, was
applied to people that were brought up with a different background. And
if you're not, even if you know you're Jewish, but a different
you're brought up in a different type of Judaism, they use this
concept of תינוק שנשבה, interestingly, although you bring a חטאת. So they,
but they used it because conceptually it indicates an idea of אונס,
of that you cannot actually be held to fault for this type
of if you were brought up in this different way. Yes.
I finally got around to idolatry at the end, but idolatry is
forbidden even for non-Jews, even when we don't teach them.
That's an interesting question, I'll have to
think about it.